<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The secret history of the most renowned Q. Elizabeth and the E. of Essex by a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Person of quality.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59022</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12530442</idno>
  <idno type="VID">62767</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240951142</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8814</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12530442</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 293:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The secret history of the most renowned Q. Elizabeth and the E. of Essex by a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 73, [2], 61, [3] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will with the wisp ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cologne :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts; the second pt. has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Has frontispiece, a woodcut of Elizabeth and Essex.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements ([3] p.) at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Fiction.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1566-1601 --  Fiction.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="frontispiece">
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>The E: of ESSEX and Q: ELIZEBETH novell.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:1"/>
                  <p>THE Secret HISTORY OF THE MOST RENOWNED <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> AND THE <hi>E, of Essex.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By a Person of Quality.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COLOGNE:</hi> Printed for <hi>Will with the Wisp,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Moon in the Ecliptick,</hi> 1680.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="novel_part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62767:2"/>
                  <head>THE EARL of <hi>ESSEX:</hi> OR, THE AMOURS OF Queen <hi>ELIZABETH.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The First Part.</head>
                  <div type="narration">
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE People had seen <hi>Essex</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary favour with the <hi>Queen;</hi> and were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more surpriz'd at his Fall. She had rais'd him to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62767:3"/>highest Dignities of Her King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and he continued then General of Her Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> against the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> who had rais'd a Rebellion there. His Endeavours to divert his Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune were vain; and after an obstinate Resistance, he was brought up to <hi>London,</hi> and confin'd to his House.</p>
                     <p>The Services he had done the State by his Valour, were very considerable; but the Favours the <hi>Queens</hi> Goodness had heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on him, proceeded from a more secret Cause, and more pressing Motives. Had the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> never signaliz'd himself by the Glory of his Actions, the Kindness She had for him would have made Her distinguish him from the rest of Her Subjects: And 'tis certain, Her Affection had made him Her Favourite,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62767:3"/>before he could pretend to it in the least by his Services. She was highly Renowned above the Women of Her Time, for Courage, and Strength of Mind; yet too Weak, to be Proof against the Impressions of Love. She had a passionate Tenderness for the unfortunate Criminal; which was his Advocate, and defended him from the Severity of Justice; and was so far from taking pleasure in a publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of him, that She abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Her Heart, those cruel Maxims that crost Her Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p>She kept Her Bed to prevent publick Discovery of a Trouble it was not in Her Power to hide: And admitting of no Company, but the Countess of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> (Her intimate Confident) She gave Vent to Her Tears, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62767:4"/>freely lamented the Misfortune that threatned the Repose of Her Life.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Countess</hi> had a little sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the <hi>Queens</hi> Inclinations; and thought her self obliged by powerful Reasons, to find out the Misery. But this being a tender Point, and having to deal with a <hi>Princess</hi> naturally of a very high Spirit, the <hi>Countess</hi> was silent. But the <hi>Queens</hi> Grief was too violent, to continue long Mute: Her Sighs confirm'd the Suspicions of the <hi>Countess;</hi> and Her repeating in Her Trouble, the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>'s Name, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd the <hi>Countess</hi> of the Truth of what till then she had but slightly fancy'd.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Countess</hi> had that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of her self, she easily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd her Concern in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture; and appearing only
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62767:4"/>sensible of the Trouble of the <hi>Queen,</hi> she us'd all the Art she had to comfort Her; and fail'd not to put Her in mind, how serviceable on that occasion Her Vertue might be to Her, which had already made Her the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the World.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ah, Madam!</hi> (says the <hi>Queen,</hi> interrupting her) <hi>You do not yet know Me. The Force I have long put upon My Self, hath made you think, with the rest of the World, That the Heighth of my Spirit, hath raised Me above the Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Nature; and the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of my Thoughts, secur'd Me from the Troubles of Life. But, Alas! poor</hi> Elizabeth <hi>is a Slave to Her Weakness; and hath all this while but sacrificed to Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all the Quiet of Her Soul, and Happiness of Her Days. 'Tis high time, Madam, to reveal the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62767:5"/>Misery. My Heart, Madam, is sensible and susceptible of the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Impressions: And what I have, in appearance, condemn'd most, is perhaps the only thing has most Power over Me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The</hi> Earl of Essex <hi>is no less Famous for the Victory gain'd over My Heart, than for his Treasons against Me: And I, who have maintain'd the Freedom of My Soul, and preserv'd the Liberty of My Affection, from submitting to the Efforts of all the Princes of</hi> Europe, <hi>and the Greatest of My Subjects, have now the Misfortune to find my Inclinations violently sway'd in Favour of a Person, as Ʋngrateful as Faithless. You know what I have done to Raise him; nor can you be ignorant, how ill he hath Requited Me by his Crimes. A Man, who being Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of</hi> Ireland, <hi>General of my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62767:5"/>Army, in quiet Possession of the b st Offices of My Kingdom, and Master of My Affection; yet could not forbear Conspiring against that Authority I was but too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to Give him a Share of; and perhaps, against a Life I took no other Pleasure in, but the Opportunities I had by it, to make His Happy</hi>—</p>
                     <p>It was not in the <hi>Queens</hi> Power to say a word more: And the <hi>Countess,</hi> more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily concern'd at the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, grew so much the more Curious; and pretending to Comfort the <hi>Queen,</hi> Engag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d her dextrously to a further Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No, Madam,</hi> (replyes the <hi>Queen</hi>) <hi>There's no Hope of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for Me, if the</hi> Earl of Essex <hi>Dye. By the Condition you see his Imprisonment hath put Me in,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62767:6"/>you may guess what I am like to be Reduced to by his Death. His Crimes I Abhor, but am in Love with his Person; and find, that as I have been so Weak to let him know it, I shall again be so Weak to Pardon him all. You do not know his Carriage towards Me. And perhaps, My Affection will as easily find Excuses for his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, as it did for My Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. I will give you the Relation of it; but Conjure you to Reproach Me so plainly with the Shame I expose My Self to, that I may at last prevail with My Self, to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Ingratefullest of Men, to the Rigour of his Fate.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="Queens_narration">
                     <p>I Shall not give you an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Interests of <hi>England,</hi> other than what the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> stands concern'd in, I will pass by the Obstacles
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62767:6"/>rais'd against My Establishment; and tell you only, I quickly gain'd Possession of the Throne, was Ador'd of My People, and Happy beyond the Hopes of a Person of My Sex. But <hi>Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is not always attended with the Pleasure of Life; and that smooth Gale of Felicity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose in the beginning of My Reign, quickly blew over, at least in My Opinion.</p>
                     <p>Being settled in My Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I found My <hi>Court</hi> throng'd with Suitors of Sovereign Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, striving to merit the Choice it was in My Power (at once) to make of a <hi>Husband,</hi> and a <hi>King:</hi> The Earls of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset, Leicester, Arundel,</hi> and <hi>Hertford,</hi> had most Right to pretend to it. But finding My Self disturbed by their Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities in My most serious Affairs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62767:7"/>and not at all inclin'd to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Suits; I formally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd to them, I design'd to Live single; and endeavoured to make them amends by consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Imployments, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyances I bestow'd on them. Three of them openly quitted the Hopes they had conceived: Only the Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> more Ambitious, (or more Constant) than the rest, kept a foot his Pretensions, and publickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his Services: But it was not ordain'd, his Perseverance should be Crown'd with the Reward of My Affection.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> having sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliz'd himself against the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Earls of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Westmerland,</hi> made about this Time his first Appearance at <hi>Court;</hi> and found with more ease the Secret to please Me.</p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62767:7"/>
                     <p>Those who presented him to Me, spoke much in Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of him. And I was too much an Eye-witness of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his Person. I look'd upon him, as an Extraordinary Man. Nor could I but think it equally Extraordinary, to find My Self so strangely affected with him at the first Sight. The Reception I gave him, was very Obliging; and the Acknowledgements he made Me, were full of Respect: So that, for the time, I saw no Cause to check My Inclination.</p>
                     <p>I may Date from this first View, the loss of my Repose. I presently fell into a Disquiet I had till then been altogether a Stranger to: And in spite of My high Spirit, I could not but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly acknowledge the Cause. And all the Efforts of My haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Humour against it, serv'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62767:8"/>only to make the Triumph of the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> more Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                     <p>You would better compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Condition I was in, did you know the Resentments of a Great Soul, jealous of its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, in Extremities of this Nature; the Combats it under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes, and the Confusion that attends the Defence.</p>
                     <p>I fear'd My Eyes would dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Pleasure I took, in Looking on the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> and My Weakness occasion Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses in the World, to the Prejudice of My Glory. I shun'd the Sight of him; but to little purpose, when I carry'd the <hi>Idea</hi> of him in My Heart. I was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with My Self for it, and sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd My Reason to My Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to deface it: But <hi>Love</hi> had so violently seiz'd My Heart,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62767:8"/>that I struggled in vain to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possess him.</p>
                     <p>By little and little, I yielded My Self Captive to that Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inclination, which had at first sight made Me so much in Love with the Person of the <hi>Earl of Essex:</hi> And pretending the Services he had done Me against the Earls of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Westmerland,</hi> and the Memory I had of the Good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of his Father, as the ground of My Favour, I made him <hi>Knight of the Garter, Master of the Horse,</hi> and of the <hi>Privy-Council,</hi> though under Age.</p>
                     <p>Thus did I Cherish and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge the Weakness I had so long struggled with, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd My Self for. The high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er he grew in Office, the nearer he was to My Person. His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaisance, his Respect, his Looks,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62767:9"/>(which to Me appear'd all Kind and Languishing) and especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally My Affection, which had Tenderness enough, to give a favourable Construction to the least of his Actions, conspir'd to Betray Me.</p>
                     <p>Envy rais'd him Enemies: The Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi> (concern'd to be Jealous of him) quickly suspected the Truth. And look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> as a Person of Merit, capable to cross his Pretensions, he made it his business to Supplant him; which I presently observ'd. I easily fore-saw the Trouble My Favour might cause between Persons so Considerable: And the better to countenance the Kindness I had for <hi>Essex,</hi> I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected a little Complaisance for <hi>Leicester,</hi> which somewhat aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Edge of his Jealousie.</p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62767:9"/>
                     <p>About that Time, the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Swede,</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> for his Son, and the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Anjou,</hi> made Me their several Proposals of Marriage, which I was forc'd to Receive; but wanted not Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to send Home their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadors, without any Fruit of their Negotiation.</p>
                     <p>How contrary to the real Motive of My Actions, were the Interpretations Men made of My Refusal of Marriage with these <hi>Princes!</hi> It redound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much to My Honour; My Glory was increas'd by it, and the World admir'd My Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Love,</hi> even then when My Soul was wholly possest by it.</p>
                     <p>The Aversion I exprest for Forreign Allyances, rais'd the Hopes of the Earl of <hi>Leicester;</hi> and <hi>Essex</hi> seem'd over-joyed at
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62767:10"/>it: <hi>Not</hi> (said he, as I heard af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards) <hi>but that the</hi> Queen <hi>is Discreet in all Her Actions; and Her Choice, had She made One, had been Decent and Just: But that I think Her so fit to Reign alone, that I could not without extream Trouble, see Her share Her Authority with a Husband, who perhaps would in time be Her Master.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Construction I made of the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>'s Zeal, was suitable to My Affection, and the Desire I had of gaining his Heart; which I wish'd so passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, that I fancy'd it done; and that the pretended Severity, that made Me slight <hi>Kings,</hi> was the only thing that frightned his Respect; and that he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd his Love to Me, could he have thought he durst presume to do it.</p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62767:10"/>
                     <p>The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alanson</hi> (not discourag'd by My refusal of his Brother) began soon after to make Addresses for himself; and it was not in My Power, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny My Consent for his Voyage to <hi>London.</hi> But what Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages soever he pleaded in his Favour, certain it is, the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> lost not any he had gain'd over Me. The Stay of that <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd the <hi>Earl</hi>'s Interest: He was constantly at My Elbow. When the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alanson</hi> spoke to Me, methought I read Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches against My Self, in the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>'s Eyes. The Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi> watched Me as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; though not with equal Regard from Me. I rais'd so many Difficulties against the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alanson</hi>'s Design, that he was forc'd to desist: And I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62767:11"/>rid My Hands of his Person, and his Suit, without giving him Cause of Complaint.</p>
                     <p>You know, that after the Death of the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Scots,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> (who still makes himself indispensibly subject to a Necessity of Opposing Me) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a League with the <hi>Pope,</hi> against Me. And having fill'd the World with Injurious Declarations against My Right to the Crown, they joyn'd all their Forces, to pull it off My Head. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> made themselves, on the sudden, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of <hi>Daventer:</hi> The <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Parma</hi> laid Siege to <hi>Sluys.</hi> It was high time to provide for Defence; and the Earl of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> was sent away with all the Nobility of the Kingdom, in the Head of a numerous Army. The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was one of the first
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62767:11"/>to follow him: And as strongly inclin'd as I was to stay him, yet I thought, the Man I lov'd, ought not to be Idle, when he had Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity by Glorious Actions, to merit the Kindness I had for him.</p>
                     <p>I will not spend time, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you a Relation of a War, which perhaps you are suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently inform'd of, and concerns not the Secrets of My Life. It tended to Our Advantage; all (to the very Winds) having favour'd Our Side. When the Generals of the Army arriv'd at <hi>London,</hi> I was carry'd in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to St. <hi>Pauls:</hi> Yet the Joy I had to see the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> was greater than that for the signal Victory obtain'd. Amongst an infinite number of Persons of several Ranks, My Eyes were fixt only on him: And much
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62767:12"/>ado I had, sometimes, out of Policy, to cast a Look on the Earl of <hi>Leicester.</hi> Both of them had done very Great Actions: I commended them publickly; and particularly, joy'd the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> for the Success of his Valor and Conduct; who spoke so much in Praise of the Valor and Conduct of the Earl of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> that he was forc'd in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital, to do him Right, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him openly the <hi>Elogies</hi> he deserv'd.</p>
                     <p>Not long after this Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> fell into a very deep Melancholy. I was the first that perceiv'd it; and took it for an Effect of some se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Passion. I wish'd now and then, he would once take the Boldness to declare himself; but presently My Reason, upon <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Thoughts,</hi> set before My
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62767:12"/>Eyes the Confusion would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly follow an Explication of that Nature to the Ruin of My Reputation, and that high E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem the World had for Me: Yet (to speak Truth) I could not resolve what to do, or to wish. I am in Love; I desir'd to be lov'd again; and that was all I could make of it.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> in the mean time, continued Sad: I was troubled to see him so; and fancying My Self the cause, I was desirous to know it; and resolved to fetch it out of him.</p>
                     <p>He had full Liberty of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess to Me; and I enlarg'd it dayly: But not to Expose My Reputation in forcing him to declare himself, I pretended an Inclination to Favour the Earl of <hi>Leicester;</hi> who since his late
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62767:13"/>Victories, and entertain'd New Hopes.</p>
                     <p>One Day, as the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> came to thank Me for the Government of <hi>Ireland</hi> I had bestow'd on him, I was loth to lose the Opportunity; and, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting what he would have said in Ackuowleddgment: <hi>You need not enlarge your self</hi> (said I) <hi>on a thing, I am fully assur'd of. I take Pleasure in Raising your Fortune; and wish I could as easily remove your Melancholy, as I am pleas'd to give a New Proof of the Sense I have of your Service. You may, in your Turn, oblige Me</hi> (added I) <hi>who am fallen into a Troublesom Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and find it very difficult to reduce My Affections into a Complyance with the Necessity of the State. This presses me hard to provide</hi> England <hi>a</hi> King: <hi>This
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62767:13"/>Choice is difficult; and I have not a Mind to make it among Forreigners. You are Discreet, and (I have Reason to believe) not the least Loving of My Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. I will take your Advice; speak your Mind freely, what Man in</hi> England <hi>you think best deserves this Fortune.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I look't on him with that Kindness, as would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spir'd the most Feareful with Boldness: I observed in his Eyes extraordinary Emotions, and all the Symptoms of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ready to break out. The Point appear'd Tender, and My Imagination flatter'd Me, all would be as I wish'd. <hi>Your Majesties Resolution</hi> (answers he) <hi>will render a Man more Glorious by the Quality of Your Husband, than of the Greatest Monarch on Earth. Remember</hi>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62767:14"/>(said I) <hi>I expect not a</hi> Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick, <hi>hut Advice from You: And that your Business, at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, is to Nominate the Man I am to Make</hi> King; <hi>not to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his Good Fortune, in being so. The Business is so nice, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> (replyes he) <hi>I dare not Speak my Mind, though Your Majesty order it. Did you know</hi> (said I) <hi>what moves Me to this Confidence in you, you would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps express your selfwith a great deal more Freedom. But because, to bring you to it, I must pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further; tell Me, Whether you think the Earl of</hi> Leicester <hi>deserves to be your</hi> Prince? <hi>The Earl of</hi> Leicester (answers he) <hi>is Well-Born, and a Person of Great Merit, and will answer the Honour your Majesty intends him. Is that all you have to say to Me?</hi> said I. <hi>Ah Madam!</hi> (answers
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62767:14"/>he with a Sigh, which made Me expect something more Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing) <hi>I should have more to say to you for my Self, then the Ears of</hi> Leicester. <hi>What hinders you?</hi> (said I.) <hi>The respect I have for Your Majesty,</hi> answered he. <hi>I am in Love, Madam; but 'tis not a thing fitting, to make my</hi> Queen <hi>my Confident.</hi> I Blush'd at those Words, and was in a mind not to proceed further. But I look't upon him; and there needed no more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare My Weakness: <hi>I have that Esteem from you</hi> (added I) <hi>that I am not unwilling to be of your Councel. Well, Madam, since you will have it so</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues he) <hi>I must acquaint You, I am desperately in Love with the Countess of</hi> Rutland; <hi>and that I cannot Live, if your Majesty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent not, that she shall make me hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62767:15"/>
                     <p>You may easily guess what an Astonishment I was in at this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; having, upon so good Grounds, expected to have heard My Self named. It was well for Me, I had not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lost the Haughtiness of My Nature: The poor Remains of it were My only Help to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve Me from discovering more Weakness to the <hi>Earl,</hi> than he had discover'd Love for his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress. His Transports help'd Me to cover Mine: He perceiv'd not the Blow he had given Me. And sacrificing My Grief to My Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I affected to appear calm and unconcern'd, when My Soul was full of Trouble and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. <hi>You have made a good Choice</hi> (said I) <hi>and the Countess of</hi> Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>will very well deserve the Kindness you profess for her. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> (replyes he, with Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62767:15"/>in his Looks, which height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned My Grief) <hi>You have done more for me, in approving the Passion I have for the Countess of</hi> Rutland, <hi>than You could have done, had You procur'd Me the Empire of the Ʋniverse. It is your Desire then</hi> (added I, with a Sigh My Despair forc'd from Me) <hi>that I should give her to you. I desire any thing</hi> (says he) <hi>that may preserve me from dying for Love of her. Go your way then</hi> (said I, to be rid of him, and ease My Self of the intolerable Constraint I was under) <hi>Be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sur'd, I will concern My Self in your Amour: You shall know it in time. But take heed you give not the Earl of</hi> Leicester <hi>the least in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of the Secret I have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to you. Not before I have Order from Your Majesty</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer'd he) <hi>to congratulate his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62767:16"/>Happiness, and pay him the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voirs of an Affectionate Subject.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Had you seen with what an Ayr he pronounced these words, you would have abhorr'd him for his Ingratitude. As for Me, I was left in so desperate a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, it was long e're I could recover My Reason out of the Entanglements of <hi>Love, Anger,</hi> and <hi>Jealousie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was partly the Author of My Misfortune, by calling to <hi>Court</hi> the Countess of <hi>Rutland,</hi> after her Husband's Death, without considering she was one of the handsomest Ladies on Earth; and but Sixteen Years old. I had not observed any particular Kindness the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> had for her: He visited her as other Ladies of the <hi>Court.</hi> But their Intrigue was mysterious; and the more secretly it was carry'd,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62767:16"/>the Engagement was the strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the Affection more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                     <p>It is impossible to express the Trouble I was in, when <hi>Anger</hi> seiz'd the Place <hi>Grief</hi> had possest in my Heart. Though the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> had been ignorant of his good Fortune, I could not forbear reproaching him for slighting it as he did; and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got not to charge him with Treachery and Ingratitude. But when I consider'd he was so far from apprehending My mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he was gone directly to make a solemn Tender of his Love to another, and carry her the joyful News of his Success with Me; I resolved, at least, to delay the Pleasure of it for a time; and went out of My Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set into My Chamber, to call him back. I thought I heard
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62767:17"/>the Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi>'s Voice, and his, in the <hi>Anti-Chamber;</hi> and going to the Door, found I was not mistaken. <hi>Leicester</hi>'s Jealousie, had, in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, made him watch <hi>Essex</hi> as he entred my Chamber; and when he saw him return with Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in his Looks: <hi>You are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> (says he) <hi>in a Priviledge, to entertain the</hi> Queen <hi>as long as you please; when others, who as passionately desire it, cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that Happiness for a moment. I am perswaded</hi> (replyes <hi>Essex</hi>) <hi>you better deserve it; and make no doubt, but you will find more Pleasure in it. I will leave you at liberty to go in Search of it; and you may do me a Favour, not to stay me, being call'd another way, on a very pressing Occasion.</hi> He had no sooner said so, but he went his way; and I was so
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62767:17"/>confounded with this new Sight, I scarce knew where I stood.</p>
                     <p>Having at length recover'd My Reason, I had the Discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to hide My Weakness. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently My Anger would have vented it self on the Countess of <hi>Rutland:</hi> But I consider'd, her only Crime was her Beauty; and that she knew not My Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for her Servant.</p>
                     <p>The Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi> having at his entrance perceiv'd Me in Disorder, durst not take notice of it; but after a short Visit, withdrew.</p>
                     <p>A little before, I had sent to Congratulate the King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var,</hi> upon his coming to the Crown of <hi>France;</hi> and having Intelligence he wanted Aid to secure his Government, I resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to send him some under the Conduct of the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62767:18"/>in hopes his Absence might Cure Me. I would have perswaded My Self, the Cause of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving him on that Occasion, was My Desire to forget him: But upon second Thoughts, I must confess, it was rather the Desire of removing him out of the Sight of a beloved Rival.</p>
                     <p>Being resolved on the Point, I hastned the Execution; and having ordered the <hi>Earl of Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex</hi> to attend Me: <hi>You love Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> (said I to him) <hi>and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think, you will prefer the Pleasure of Sighing before a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striss, to the Opportunities of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring Glory: I have provided One for you; and am resolv'd, you shall Command the Troops I am sending to the</hi> French King. <hi>And to fortifie your self against the Troubles of Absence, you need only think of the Pleasures of a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62767:18"/>Return.</hi> His Answer was only in Sighs; and that passionate Language made Me hasten his Departure.</p>
                     <p>Soon after, the Countess of <hi>Rutland</hi> (whom I could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear using very coldly) desir'd leave to go into the Countrey, a considerable distance from <hi>London.</hi> I had then so little Love for her, I did not desire to have her near Me; but readily consented she should retire.</p>
                     <p>The Hopes she had to see the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> return, supported her so, that she, with much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, saw him take his leave: But I am assur'd by Experience, the Grief for his Departure, equall'd (at least) the Hopes of his Return.</p>
                     <p>When he was Arriv'd in <hi>France,</hi> Fame spoke aloud in Commendation of him: His Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62767:19"/>alter'd not My Affection; and, in spite of all I could do to the contrary, I had a sensible Pleasure to hear him commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                     <p>Had I been desir'd, I should have call'd him Home as soon as <hi>France</hi> was in Peace: But I sent him new Orders to joyn Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Howard,</hi> who was going for <hi>Spain:</hi> And I gave him the like Commission for this Expedition, as for that of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He did Wonders in <hi>Spain:</hi> His single Valour frightned the Enemies. And having taken <hi>Cales,</hi> and pillag'd the Coast of <hi>Portugal,</hi> he put again to <hi>Sea</hi> for <hi>England.</hi> The Fleet was scattered by a Storm, and We had News the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was lost. Then it was, I knew bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ever, the Kindness I had for him. I could no longer
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62767:19"/>perswade My Self, that his Indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference for Me deserv'd Mine for him.</p>
                     <p>I accus'd the <hi>Sea</hi> a Thousand times, for having taken too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable a Revenge for Me; and was under Sufferings more cruel than Death, when News was brought Me, that by the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of the Admiral of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he was Arriv'd at <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth;</hi> from whence, in few days, he came to <hi>Court.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To shew you how little Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son we have, when we are in Love, and how fickle are the Resolutions of a tender Heart, though provoked by Slights and Contempts: I had lamented the Death of the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> and receiv'd the News of his being Alive with a thousand Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Joy. I was extreamly pleas'd with the Report of his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62767:20"/>Arrival at <hi>London.</hi> But when I consider'd I should see him full of Love for another, and that perhaps I should not be able to conceal My Jealousie, I was tempted to order him to give the <hi>Council</hi> an Account of his Conduct, and not admit him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to My Presence. I was some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of the Opinion, I should be able to do so: But this weak Heart of Mine, so prepossest in favour of him, revolted against all My Resolutions. I must fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low My Inclinations, and see the most dangerous Enemy of My Repose, the Troubler of My Rest. He came to <hi>Whitehall:</hi> I admitted him to My Presence: I lookt upon him; and, spite of all My high Spirit, he saw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Kindness in all My Actions.</p>
                     <p>You may imagine, what an
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62767:20"/>agreeable Surprize it was to Me, to find at our first Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that Absence had wean'd his Affections from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of <hi>Rutland.</hi> He appear'd no longer in that Langushing Melancholy I observ'd him in, before his Departure: He had Satisfaction in his Looks: The Air of his Actions were Smooth and Calm. And I fancy'd as much Joy in his Face, (though the Countess of <hi>Rutland</hi> was Absent) as I felt in My Self at the Explication he made. <hi>I see you again return'd with Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory,</hi> (said I:) <hi>But am sorry, it is not in My Power to reward your last with a Sight of the Countess of</hi> Rutland. <hi>But if any thing I can do, can comfort you — I am easily Comforted for her Absence, when I am permitted to see Your Majesty,</hi> (answer'd
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62767:21"/>he.) <hi>I have no Passion now, but for the Glory of Serving Your Majesty; and the Countess of</hi> Rutland <hi>is now to me, no more than other Ladies of the</hi> Court. <hi>Are you not longer in Love with the Countess of</hi> Rutland? (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed I, between Joy and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust.) <hi>You have spoken too fast. When you see her again — When I see her again</hi> (sayes he, interrupting Me) <hi>it shall be without those Transports I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest for her, not forgetting the Respects due to your Majesty. What,</hi> (answered I) <hi>are you not afraid of the Reproaches of a provoked Mistriss? No Madam</hi> (said he, in a free and unconcern'd man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:) <hi>All I am concern'd for, is to do my Duty, and approve My Self worthy your Majesties Favour. This</hi> (answer'd I) <hi>deserves My Acknowledgment; and time
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62767:21"/>shall let You see, I am not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus did the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> assure Me, he was Cur'd of his first passion: And I was in Hopes, it might be in My power, to see him one Day entertain another. A Week after, he desir'd Leave to go into the Country about his Private Affairs: He was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent a Fortnight; and return'd more calm, and unconcern'd, than ever.</p>
                     <p>The Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi> had doubled his Importunities, in the Absence of the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Me, at last, to put him out of Hopes. He is naturally Bold; and was so blown up with the Opinion of the Glory he had gain'd by some Late Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he proceeded to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62767:22"/>telling Me plainly, <hi>He was Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Earl of</hi> Essex: And would have made a Crime of the Discourse I told you of, past between them, as <hi>Essex</hi> left My Chamber. The Answer I made him, was an Absolute Command, <hi>He should be Silent:</hi> Which was so far obey'd, that after some dayes Murmuring, he held his Peace. Yet this put Me in mind to observe some measures, and not to follow openly My Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
                     <p>Things continued in this State, till the Troubles of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> I have often open'd My Mouth, to let the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> know the Advantages he had over Me; but Modesty shut it again: Yet seeing him under a Necessity of going for <hi>Ireland,</hi> when the Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi> had rais'd a General Rebellion, I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62767:22"/>had not the power to let him take Leave, without acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, <hi>The Kingdom was at his Command.</hi> Upon the first News of the Troubles, he threw himself at my Feet, begging the Honour of My Command to go Quiet those Disorders. <hi>You have done enough,</hi> (said I) <hi>and there's no need you should (by exposing your self to New Dangers) oblige Me to New Acknowledgments. I doubt not, Madam,</hi> (answer'd he) <hi>but the Favour I beg of Your Majesty, will be envy'd me: But I take the Boldness to say, Your Majesty cannot refuse it me, without doing your self Injury: It being an Occasion may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to my Meriting the Favour you have already Honour'd me with. The Ardour you express for undertaking Great Actions,</hi> (replyed I) <hi>is not perhaps so
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62767:23"/>Pleasing, as you imagine: And all the Good that may Redound to</hi> England <hi>though your Valour, is less Considerable, than the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is given Me, who take less Care of My Crown, than your Life. I am Ambitious: Yet— Ah! My Lord, Save Me the Confusion of a more particular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of what you ought and might easily have long since un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood. I might perhaps, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume too far in my Wishes,</hi> sayes the <hi>Earl,</hi> in some Disorder. <hi>Wish boldly,</hi> (answer'd I) <hi>I Love you; And if I Blush to tell you so, 'tis not that I am either Asham'd, or Repent of it. You may believe this Acknowledgment a very hard Task for a Person of My Humour, who have seen you Sigh for another; when I slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Kings <hi>for your Sake, and would have Sacrificed more to your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62767:23"/>What, Madam!</hi> (cryes he, like a man astonisht) <hi>Have You lov'd me, and I been so Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, to make my self unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Your Kindness by those Sighs I now disavow? Did My Eyes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tell you what I lookt for in Yours?</hi> said I. <hi>I never had the Boldness</hi> (answer'd he) <hi>to make any such Construction of Your Looks. Your Fear was the Effect of Indifference,</hi> (said I) <hi>But no more of what's past. Tell Me now, Can you love Me? Rather ask me, Madam,</hi> (answers he) <hi>if all the Affection of my Soul can me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Your Love? And, Whether the Earl of</hi> Leicester <hi>(whom You design to make the happiest Man on Earth) shall not carry the Day from me? The Earl of</hi> Leicester (said I) <hi>was but a Pretence to make you speak. I told you then truly, the Thoughts I had of you.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62767:24"/>My Trouble for you was not small, both in your Absence, and since your Return: But all is forgotten. Be henceforth as I wish, and doubt not of being happy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He answer'd Me with some Disorder, which I fancy'd the Effect of unexpected Joy. I thought it time to be no longer Scrupulous; and that it was in vain to have any Reserves, when I had said so much. <hi>I will not let you go under any Ʋncertainty,</hi> (proceeded I) <hi>but to convince you clearly of the Truth of what I've said, take This,</hi> (said I, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering him a <hi>Ring,</hi> as the highest Mark of My Favour) <hi>keep it as a Pledge of My Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; which I conjure you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve in the State it is in: And on that condition, I promise you, never to deny you any thing you shall desire of Me, when you shew
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62767:24"/>Me this <hi>Ring,</hi> though it cost Me My Life, and My Fortune.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Joy and Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at receiving the <hi>Ring,</hi> were in appearance, extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and unparallel'd; and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Promises of as high a nature.</p>
                     <p>He went for <hi>Ireland</hi> in few days, leaving Me fully perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Thoughts were wholly taken up with Me. But he had scarce Advanc'd up to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,</hi> but he was Charg'd with all the Crimes which occasion'd his Imprisonment, and that of the Earl of <hi>Southampton.</hi> Then it was, I began to repent I had not given Ear to the wholsom Advice <hi>Cecil</hi> would have given Me, concerning the secret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the <hi>Earl of Essex.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In a word, While My Thoughts were wholly imploy'd
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62767:25"/>to make his Fortune glorious, he was plotting with the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> to surprize and make Me Prisoner in this Palace.</p>
                     <p>You know the rest, <hi>Madam;</hi> His obstinate Resistance, his want of Respect for My Orders, his Imprisoning My Ministers, his Murthering My Souldiers, and his intolerable Pride in all his Misfortunes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="narration">
                     <p>Thus ended the <hi>Queens</hi> Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course; which having call'd fresh to Her Mind, all that had pass'd between Her and <hi>Essex,</hi> She was more troubled than ever.</p>
                     <p>The Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> hath heard Her, with Attention suitable to her great Concern, in the Discourse. She, as well as the <hi>Queen</hi> had been in Love with the <hi>Earl;</hi> and advanc'd
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62767:25"/>many steps, (but in vain) to raise a Passion in him: And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving newly understood the cause of his slighting her, it added in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely to her former Resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>She had no mind to condemn the <hi>Queens</hi> Weakness, knowing her self guilty of the like: Nor was she inclin'd to speak in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a man, who was grown so much the more odious to her, as she had formerly passionately lov'd him. She thought it suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to comfort the <hi>Queen</hi> with Discourses, that seem'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed only from Zeal for her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; when, in truth, her Thoughts were wholly bent for the Ruine of an ingrateful Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; who, in her Judgement, deserv'd nothing but Hatred at her Hands.</p>
                     <p>Though <hi>Love</hi> thought not fit
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62767:26"/>the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> should admire the Countess of <hi>Nottingham;</hi> yet another was her Captive, whose Character did (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) make her amends: It was Secretary <hi>Cecil;</hi> who amidst his great Offices, and the Gravity that became them, discover'd in the Beauty, Ingenuity, and high Spirit of the Countess of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> some Charms, that made him capable of a strong Passion for her; which was heightned by the Hatred both of them had profest against the <hi>Earl of Essex; Cecil</hi> having always lookt on him as the invincible Obstacle of his ambitious Pretensions: And the Countess had against him, all the Rage and Aversion, that usually succeed Kindness abus'd.</p>
                     <p>They were glad of the Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment of the <hi>Earl of Essex;</hi> but the favourable Inclinations
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62767:26"/>the <hi>Queen</hi> exprest for him, Alarm'd them.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Countess</hi> had no sooner taken leave of the <hi>Queen,</hi> but she gave <hi>Cecil</hi> an Account of all she had learnt. Having consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the Consequences, they concluded it necessary, while their <hi>Princess</hi> sigh'd secretly for the Prisoner, means should be found by private ways, and an artful Conduct, (without their appearing to have any such De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign) to take away the Mercy, which <hi>Love</hi> might inspire into Her.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cecil,</hi> for the first Step, press'd the <hi>Queen</hi> to bring <hi>Essex</hi> to his Tryal; and caus'd certain News of his Death, to be spread throughout <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Essex,</hi> in the mean time, was busi'd with Thoughts of more weight, than those of his Life.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62767:27"/>He knew well enough, his <hi>Queen</hi> lov'd him; and knew as well, he had deceiv'd Her; and that She might with a great deal of Justice, not only <hi>Reproach,</hi> but <hi>Condemn</hi> him.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> had not seen him since his going into <hi>Ireland:</hi> But having not the power to give him up to his ill Fortune, without having heard him, She resolv'd to go to his House, (where he was Prisoner) to Reproach him, as he deserv'd; and endeavour, if possible, to find him innocent.</p>
                     <p>It is not far from <hi>Whitehall</hi> to <hi>Essex-House:</hi> And the <hi>Queen</hi> took so good Order in the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that no notice was taken of the Undecency of the Visit; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been introduced by Her Confidents alone into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Criminal.</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:62767:27"/>
                     <p>He was surpriz'd at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the <hi>Queen:</hi> The lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing Condition She was in, made Her sigh. All went for him, and the Victory seem'd ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie. He saluted Her with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Respect: And then fixing on Her Face, those Eyes of his, which had so often charm'd Her, he fetcht some Tears from Hers. <hi>Well, My Lord,</hi> (says She, dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them) <hi>you see what I do for you, notwithstanding all the Crimes I can reproach you with. I am come to you; and with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to hear you, if you have any thing to say, to justifie your self. I have lov'd you too well, not to wish it above all things: And, would Heaven were pleas'd, your Justification might be purchas'd with any (the most precious) Thing in My Power. My greatest Crime is, That I thought my self too hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62767:28"/>Madam,</hi> replyes the <hi>Earl,</hi> sighing. <hi>Had you rested there,</hi> (said the <hi>Queen</hi>) <hi>I should have been too well satisfied, to have complain'd of you. But to believe your self happy, Was it necessary you should betray Me? And, Must you needs have made use of violent Means, to make your self Master of a Fortune I was willing to share with you? What Reason culd you have, to seek the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Kings of</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> Spain? <hi>Did any Interests oblige you to secret Corresponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies with</hi> Tyrone? <hi>And, Was it for the Safety of My Person, you design'd to make Me your Slave, and his? All you have done since, to My Subjects, against My Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; Are those the Expressions of your Respect? Is it by Fury and Treason, you shew your Zeal for</hi> Me <hi>and the</hi> Publick? <hi>Or, Is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62767:28"/>all We have seen and heard of you, but Illusion and Fancy? Yes, Madam,</hi> (replyes the <hi>Earl</hi>) <hi>those Accusations of Treason, and ill Designs, have run me upon the desperate Resistance I made. You have been pleas'd to heap Favours upon me; and I (too proud of what I so little deserv'd) flatter'd my self with expectation of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Pleasures, which You had not absolutely forbid me to hope for. This let loose the Envy and Jealousie of others, against my good Fortune: They abus'd Your</hi> Majesty <hi>with Mis-informations; and I had the Misfortune to be assur'd, Your</hi> Majesty <hi>had order'd I should be Arrested; though my Innocence would have perswaded me the contrary. I confess,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>I was in a Rage, to see my Enemies insult over me; being abandoned by Your</hi> Majesty, <hi>and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62767:29"/>on the point of suffering (perhaps) a shameful Death. I thought it neither for my Reputation, nor Your</hi> Majesties <hi>Honour, I should die as a Criminal. This put me upon having Recourse to those Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours and Assistances they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach me with; and the Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I took to go out of</hi> England, <hi>in hope to confound my Accusers. But I found all the Passages stopt: And I must acknowledge, in that desperate Condition, I vented my Fury, by taking Revenge on Your Ministers. They,</hi> Madam, <hi>and only They, were the Objects of the Rebellion I am charg'd with. My Design was, only they, who had so industriously labour'd to make me appear guilty, should do me Right, in declaring my Innocence; and permit me to lay it, and my Life at Your</hi> Majesties <hi>Feet. I never doubted, but Your</hi> Majesty
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62767:29"/>
                        <hi>would have done me the Honour to hear me: And that, by a clear discovery of the Truth, I should have certainly confounded the Envy of my Enemies. But their Malice hath had the Success to see me a Prisoner, hated by my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, despis'd by the World, and made a Sacrifice to their Rage: And now, What remains, but that I receive the Sentence of my Death pronounc'd by them; and see</hi> Cobham, Cecil, Rawleigh, <hi>and their Fellows, share the Favours You honour'd me with. You are well assur'd, I hate you not,</hi> (says the <hi>Queen,</hi> interrupting him:) <hi>But, Should I believe you? Yet should I not believe you? Can I give you up to the ill Fate that threatens you? I shall never mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure against Your</hi> Majesties <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> (replyes the <hi>Earl</hi>) <hi>but submit to them readily, whatever
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62767:30"/>they be. But, I confess, it would make me mad, should my Enemies have the advantage to condemn me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> knew the weak Side of the <hi>Queen;</hi> and easily reviv'd in Her, that Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness he had formerly inspir'd Her with. <hi>No,</hi> (says She, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paus'd a while) <hi>you shall not die: Make use of your Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; triumph over a Heart, whose Inclinations you very well know. I will believe your Intentions less criminal than they appear. But, My Lord, I conjure you by that Kindness of which you have such particular experience, That you give Me no Cause to repent of it. Trouble not your self for your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Honour, I will take care to repair it: And, before two days be over, I will restore you to the highest Place you ever had under Me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62767:30"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Essex,</hi> Transported with Joy for the Happy Success of this Conference, affected the <hi>Queen</hi> so much with Submissive Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, that he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor'd Her Spirits to perfect Tranquility. At parting, She promis'd to Call a <hi>Council</hi> on the Morrow; and in a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Manner, to Declare him Innocent.</p>
                     <p>As soon as it was Day, She sent for <hi>Cecil:</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> waited on Her. Having told them, in few words, of a great Conflict past between Her <hi>Justice,</hi> and Her <hi>Mercy,</hi> She concluded for the Latter; and Ordered <hi>Cecil</hi> to Summon the <hi>Council,</hi> that She might Declare to them, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign She had to set <hi>Essex</hi> at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; assuring him, She had Invincible reasons for doing so.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62767:31"/>This was a Mortal Blow to the Ambitious <hi>Cecil,</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of <hi>Nottingham.</hi> They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently Look't on one another, as if they would have ask'd each others Advice, what Course to be taken: Afterwards, they spoke to the <hi>Queen,</hi> in hopes to Divert Her; but She was In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexible: And <hi>Cecil</hi> was forc'd to order an Extraordinary Call of the <hi>Council.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But while the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>'s Enemies thought his Good Fortune on the Point of being Reconcil'd to him, <hi>Chance</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd for them with unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Success.</p>
                     <p>As the <hi>Queen</hi> was going to <hi>Council,</hi> Word was brought Her, the Countess of <hi>Rutland</hi> desir'd to wait on Her. The <hi>Queen</hi> Blush't, remembring what was past: And looking on the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62767:31"/>Request as Unseasonable and Unlucky, She was minded to have put off the <hi>Countess</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Time: But considering, She us'd not to deny any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son Access, and that the Countess of <hi>Rutland</hi> was a Lady of the best Quality; She Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, she should be Admitted; and the <hi>Countess</hi> immediately came in.</p>
                     <p>Though her Eyes languished, her looks were Sad, her Dress and her Gate very Careless; yet her Beauty was Conspicuous and Moving: She threw her self at the <hi>Queens</hi> Feet; and with Extremity of Grief in her Looks: <hi>Madam,</hi> (sayes she, with a great deal of Pain) <hi>I come to implore Your</hi> Majesties <hi>Goodness, for the Ʋnfortunate</hi> Earl of Essex. <hi>For the</hi> Earl of Essex, <hi>Madam?</hi> (answers the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62767:32"/>
                        <hi>Queen.) How come you Concern'd for him, who hath quitted you with so much Indifference after so many Promises of Extroardinary Kindness? I expect you were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come to join your Resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Mine; and desire Me to take a full Revenge, for the Injury done to your Beauty. No, Madam,</hi> (reply'd the <hi>Countess</hi>) <hi>Not the Transports of a Forsaken Mistriss, have brought me now into Your Majesties Presence; but the tender Affection due from a Virtuous Wife, to a Husband she loves: in begging for the</hi> Earl of Essex, <hi>I beg for</hi> Mine. <hi>This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession may perhaps add to our Guilt; but 'tis no Dallying for those, who are on the Brink of Destruction. I acknowledge, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, That after a thousand Cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, we had that Tender Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness one for the other, we Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62767:32"/>privatly, contrary to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect due to Your</hi> Majesty. <hi>This, Madam, this only, and his Fear of Your</hi> Majesties <hi>just Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, put the</hi> Earl of Essex <hi>upon seeking Refuge out of Your Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: He thought it fit, I should go out of Them; but never bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd a Thought of Conspiring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Your</hi> Majesty. <hi>However this hath Ruin'd us; and if You Protect not an Ʋnfortunate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, whom You have so much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd, he is Irrecoverably lost. Consider I beseech You, Madam, That a few Drops of Blood at Your Dispose, and a poor Life You are Mistriss of, are not a Revenge suitable to the Grandeur of a</hi> Queen, <hi>Ador'd for many Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; yet chiefly, for Your Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> was so astonish't at the Discourse, that the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess</hi>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62767:33"/>had full Liberty to end without Interruption. But this was sad News to a Heart late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly full of the Delights of a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing <hi>Reconciliation.</hi> What a Torrent of Anger overflowed Her Constancy? A <hi>Queen</hi> as She was, High Spirited, Haughty, and passionately in Love; to see Her Self thus cruelly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd, and find it out at a time, when a blind Credulity had stiffed all former Resentments! Yet She forced Her Self to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble Her Grief; and fixing a severe Look on the Countess of <hi>Essex: The Life you beg of Me,</hi> (sayes She) <hi>is not in My Power: The</hi> Poers <hi>are his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Ah, Madam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>yes the <hi>Countess) My husband is lost, if You give him up to their Fury: Their</hi> Jealousie <hi>will do that, which</hi> Justice <hi>cannot. Why should you
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62767:33"/>trouble your self, if he be not Guity?</hi> sayes the <hi>Queen. Though I am satisfi'd of his Innocence, Madam,</hi> (answers the <hi>Countess</hi>) <hi>yet Your Cruel Ministers are not dispos'd to believe it. Let me intreat You, Madam, (if Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty will Grant me no more) You will be pleas'd to allow me the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege of being put into the same Prison with him: I am as Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inal as he, and perhaps more. I wish it in My Power, to Grant your Desires,</hi> (sayes the <hi>Queen</hi>) <hi>but Common Policy forbids any Correspondence to be allow'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween so Considerable Persons, in your Circumstance. You may (if your please) wait his Fate, and your own, in a Chamber in this Palace. Ah, Madam!</hi> (replyes the Beautiful <hi>Countess</hi>) <hi>Consider the last Favour I beg of You, is, That I may be put into Irons. Can
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62767:34"/>you apprehend we shall Attempt any thing against you, in so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable an Estate? This is the Eve of our Greatest Disaster: That Barbarous Justice, to which you absolutely commit the Care of Your Vengeance, will to Morrow perhaps Part us for ever. Deny us not, at least, the Comfort of Mixing our last Tears. What can you fear from a Grief without Power—I fear being troubled with it; and I will be Obey'd,</hi> answers the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <hi>Queen,</hi> and goes away into Her Closet; while the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of <hi>Essex</hi> was carry'd to a Chamber, where she was left under Guard.</p>
                     <p>Never was Fury equal to the <hi>Queens:</hi> The Madness She was in to see Her Self deceiv'd, made Her for some time forget all Her Tenderness. Her Thoughts were wholly bent on Revenge, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62767:34"/>giving up to the Severity of Justice, a guitly Person She had too passionaetly Lov'd. <hi>Death!</hi> (sayes She) <hi>shall be the Reward of his Ingratitude; and I will make his Punishment an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Ʋniverse.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>With these Thoughts She came to the <hi>Council:</hi> When She had Declar'd Her Self, the <hi>Peers</hi> were nam'd for Trying the <hi>Earls of Essex</hi> and <hi>Southampton.</hi> Arm'd as She was with Resolution to do it, She trembled at the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and could not forbear mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing some amorous Sighs, with the violent Expressions her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger forc'd from Her. She with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew under very great Trouble, and admitted no Visit for seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral days.</p>
                     <p>'Tis hard to express, what a pleasing Surprize it was to <hi>Cecil,</hi> to see the <hi>Queen</hi> angry, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62767:35"/>Her Self against <hi>Essex,</hi> whom he thought Her resolv'd to pardon. He carry'd the News to the Countess of <hi>Nottingham;</hi> who was as joyful at it, as a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el person could be on such an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion. Yet they could not think all sure, while the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was only Prisoner in his House; from whence his Friends (if minded to do it) might get him out. They concluded, to take the Opportunity of the <hi>Queens</hi> Anger, to obtain Her Order for putting him into the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> which <hi>Cecil,</hi> under a cloak of Zeal for Her <hi>Majesties</hi> Service, easily gain'd, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily executed. The <hi>Earl of Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex</hi> was generally belov'd; and <hi>Cecil</hi> fearing Commotions and Tumults, if he should be carry'd through the City, order'd him to be sent to the <hi>Tower</hi> by <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:62767:35"/>Which was accordingly done.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> not able to guess at the Cause of a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess so unsuitable to the Promises of the <hi>Queen,</hi> prepar'd himself for the worst that might happen; and in few days, had Resolution enough to bear his Misfortunes. The <hi>Queen</hi> was as full of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as <hi>Cecil</hi> and the Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> were of Hopes, to see their common Enemy condemn'd in few days.</p>
                     <p>The Countess of <hi>Essex,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Comfort but her Tears, nor Company but her Fears, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd from the pity of her Guards, to have some Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of her Husband's Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. She was told, <hi>His Judges were appointed, and that he was in the Tower:</hi> Worse News she could not have. The <hi>Queen</hi>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:62767:36"/>was irreconcilably angry: Nor could she by Letter, convey with safety to her Husband, the Advice she thought good for him. A Conference she thought better; and Money being a Charm seldom resisted, she did by some Presents of Value, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with her Guards to serve her to her Mind. Having fully pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest them, she neither design'd her own Liberty, nor her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's: All she desir'd, was a minute of private Discourse with him; which her Guards under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took, and brought happily about. The Guards at the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> gain'd by their Companions, easily introduced the <hi>Countess</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Husband's Chamber.</p>
                     <p>He knew nothing of the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages at <hi>Whitehall.</hi> But when he was told, <hi>he was in few days to appear before his Judges,</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62767:36"/>with a great deal of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution and Constancy, the end of his Misfortunes; comforting himself with the Thoughts of the <hi>Countess</hi> being retired into <hi>Scotland.</hi> But seeing her so near a Danger, he thought her so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from: <hi>Ah, Madam!</hi> (says he, with Eyes full of Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness) <hi>What come you to look for in these fatal Places? And, In whose power was it, to bring you hither? My Grief, and my Guards have brought me hither?</hi> answers the Countess. <hi>What, Madam!</hi> (cryes the <hi>Earl</hi>) <hi>Are you the</hi> Queens <hi>Prisoner? And, Does She know we are Married? Yes,</hi> (replyed the <hi>Countess,</hi> mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) <hi>and is so angry, we are past Hope. I was absenting my self from you, as you had desir'd me; but the News of your Death, stopt my Retreat. And it was not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62767:37"/>in my power, to betake my self into a Place of Safety; there to attend the issue of your Troubles: If it were not in my power to ease you of them, I thought it my duty, at least, to share with you in them. This made me present my self to the</hi> Queen; <hi>and omit nothing, that might move Her Compassion: But She prov'd altogether inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Ah, Madam!</hi> (says the <hi>Earl,</hi> interrupting her,) <hi>Your Impatience hath ruin'd us: Had you not appear'd, I had been at Liberty. By a dextrous Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I had regain'd Her Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and you should have in few days, seen me come in search of you, in</hi> Scotland: <hi>But now, there's no Hopes; the</hi> Queen <hi>will be reveng'd. What?</hi> (says the <hi>Countess</hi>) <hi>Hath all I have done, tended to your Ruine? Make use of your Advantages, I conjure
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62767:37"/>you: The</hi> Queen <hi>retains some Tenderness for you; you may easily revive it. Oh! Be not a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to Her Anger. Invent any thing, in excuse of our Marriage. Disown it, if you please: I will consent to any thing, rather than see you condemn'd to Death. Let Her banish me into any part of the World; I will go most willingly. And, if, it may conduce to your Safety, make use of the</hi> Pledge <hi>She gave you.</hi> —</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ah, Madam!</hi> (replyes the <hi>Earl</hi>) <hi>Can you give such Advice to a Man, who (you know) adores you? Have you found by any of my Actions, that I love my Life more than I love you? No, I love it for nothing else, but to spend it with you: And I will part with it, with all my Heart, when I must be depriv'd of that Pleasure. My Fears were only for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62767:38"/>you; and, Can you believe, I could have the least Satisfaction in the</hi> Queens <hi>Favour, when Her Jealousie should make Her banish you? Let it break out, let Her ruine me; I will glory in my loving you, and telling it to Her Face. I know, the precious Gift She be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow'd on me, leaves me some Hopes; and I may make use of it: But I would do it with safety; and it may prevail for more than my Life. I apprehend you,</hi> (says the <hi>Countess</hi>) <hi>you would reserve all for me, and neglect your own Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But you cannot incur a Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, wherein I have not a share; and the way to preverve my Life, is to secure yours.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This Dispute lasted somewhat longer: But the <hi>Countesses</hi> Guards minding her, it was time to withdraw. She dispos'd her self, to bid her Husband <hi>Adieu.</hi>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:62767:38"/>Their Separation was moving, accompanied with abundance of Tears; to which, a multitude of tormenting Inquietudes suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, and ushered in a Day; that instead of diminishing, heightned their Sorrows.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>The End of the</hi> FIRST PART.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:39"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:39"/>
                  <p>THE Secret HISTORY OF THE MOST RENOWNED <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> AND THE <hi>E. of Essex. The Second Part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By a Person of Quality.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>COLOGNE:</hi> Printed for <hi>Will with the Wisp,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Moon in the Ecliptick,</hi> 1680.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="novel_part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:40"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62767:40"/>
                  <head>THE EARL of <hi>ESSEX:</hi> OR, THE AMOURS OF Queen <hi>ELIZABETH.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The Second Part.</head>
                  <div type="narration">
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Queen,</hi> though angry, gave no Order for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the Countess of <hi>Essex</hi> in her Husband's Impeachment. The morrow after their Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62767:41"/>the <hi>Peers</hi> met in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster-Hall,</hi> and the Earls of <hi>Essex</hi> and <hi>Southampton</hi> were brought before them by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stable</hi> of the <hi>Tower.</hi> The Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the Tryal are set forth at large, in the Histories of the Time: It shall suffice to insert here, That the Prisoners being Charg'd to have held criminal Correspondences with the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into secret Allyances with <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and Traitorously laid and carry'd on a <hi>Plot</hi> against the <hi>Queens</hi> Authority, made a very stout and resolute Defence.</p>
                     <p>As politick as <hi>Cecil</hi> was, he could not hide the Malignity of his Intentions; but it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, he was not only a severe Judge, but a dangerous Enemy: The Heat and Animosity he dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd against the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62767:41"/>were answer'd by him with a slighty Resolution, and undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Constancy. Yet, for all he could say in justification of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, he was condemn'd with the Formalities usual on such Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. Sentence was pronounced by the <hi>Lord High-Steward,</hi> That the <hi>Earls of Essex</hi> and <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton</hi> were Guilty of <hi>High-Treason,</hi> and should be Behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was not mov'd in the least, to hear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self nam'd; but appear'd hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly sorry, to find the Earl of <hi>Southampton</hi> under like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; and conjur'd the Judges, to examine with less Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, the Conduct of a Person whose only Crime was, the Love he had for him. But not able to prevail, he melted into Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of the greatest Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in the World, for his Friend.</p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62767:42"/>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> being inform'd of the Condition of Things, gave secret Orders to delay Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. She was of a high Spirit, and highly provok'd; yet found it very difficult, to raise Her Anger to a pitch equal to Her Tenderness.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cecil</hi> trembled to find the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of a Sentence deferr'd, which he had with so much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure heard pronounc'd. The Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> was equally Alarm'd.</p>
                     <p>The Proofs were but slight against the Earl of <hi>Southampton;</hi> and the <hi>Queen,</hi> sensible his long Friendship with the <hi>Earl of Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex,</hi> had chiefly engag'd him in the Matters in Charge, pardon'd his Life at the Request of his Friends.</p>
                     <p>News was brought of it to the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> whose truly brave
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62767:42"/>and generous Soul immediately broke forth into sincere Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations, <hi>He should die now with Satisfaction and Content, since the</hi> Queen <hi>had own'd by Her Pardon, the Innocence of</hi> Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton.</p>
                     <p>While the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected with a resolute Constancy, the Catastrophe of his Tragedy, the <hi>Countess</hi> (his Wife) was inform'd at <hi>Whitehall, He was Executed.</hi> Till then, she believ'd it uncertain; but this News sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd her so terribly, she fill'd the whole <hi>Court</hi> with her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations. The <hi>Queen</hi> heard them, but was not concern'd, as the rest were, for them. <hi>Let her cry,</hi> (says She to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess of <hi>Nottingham) she must shed many more, to wipe out the Score of those Tears she hath cost Me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62767:43"/>was so far from endeavouring to Pacifie the <hi>Queen,</hi> that all her Care was to keep up Her Anger. And because she was ignorant of many things she thought her self concern'd to know, she took advantage of the Trouble the Countess of <hi>Essex</hi> was in, and made her fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Visits; not to bemoan her Affliction, but to find out some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to render her more mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. It must needs have been an unparallel'd Cruelty, not to pity the handsomest Lady on Earth, appearing to our Eyes in a Condition more deplorable than can be exprest. She fell every minute, for very Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, into the Arms of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men about her; and recover'd her self only to lament the more pitifully: Which affected all but the Countess of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> who
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62767:43"/>saw all this with an Unconcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedness, suitable to the hardness of her Heart. <hi>Ah, Madam!</hi> (says the Countess of <hi>Essex,</hi> as soon as she saw her) <hi>Will you not use your Interest with the</hi> Queen, <hi>in favour of the</hi> Earl of Essex? <hi>You know my Lord of</hi> Southampton <hi>hath his Pardon,</hi> (replyes she) <hi>and the</hi> Queen, <hi>perhaps, will do as much for your Husband. Madam,</hi> (says the Countess of <hi>Essex) 'Tis not the Crimes charg'd on my Husband joyntly with the Earl of</hi> Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton, <hi>nor those common to both, that render the</hi> Queen <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable: You understand me, when I tell you, There are others She more deeply resents. And She hates the</hi> Earl of Essex <hi>less for the Attempts attributed to his Ambition, than his Engagements with me. But, Madam,</hi> (replyes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62767:44"/>the Countess of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> willing to find out the Mystery of their Love she was yet igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of) <hi>If you thought the</hi> Queen <hi>would oppose it, or be unsatisfi'd with it, Why did you not quit a Business wherein you were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nothing but Crosses? If you were ever in Love,</hi> (says the Countess of <hi>Essex) you know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, we have not always our Wits about us when we are deeply engag'd in Affection. However, Madam, when I Marry'd my Lord of</hi> Essex, <hi>I did not know the</hi> Queen <hi>was so much concern'd for him. Perhaps,</hi> (answers the Countess of <hi>Nottingham) I might do you some Service, were I throughly acquainted with particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Passages between my Lord of</hi> Essex, <hi>and</hi> You. <hi>I am not in a very fit disposition to discourse you, Madam,</hi> (says the Countess of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62767:44"/>
                        <hi>Essex.) But if I could by any Confidence, prevail with you to do something for us, I would give you an Account of all you desire. I will not promise you, I shall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prevail with the</hi> Queen: <hi>But, Madam,</hi> (adds the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Countess of <hi>Nottingham) I will use my Interest, and, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, effect more than we have Reason to hope for. Have a good Heart, Madam; Do not despair; the</hi> Queen <hi>is good: And I will zealously serve you, when I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed what Course to take.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Countess of <hi>Essex</hi> yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Perswasions of her bitterest Enemy, dry'd up her Tears; and after a short pause, spoke to this purpose.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="Countess_of_Essexs_narration">
                     <p>MY Mother Dyed very Young, lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ng no Child but me. My Father's Offices
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62767:45"/>obliging him to a Constant At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance at <hi>Court,</hi> he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Care of my Infancy to a Sister of his, settled about a Hundred Miles from <hi>London.</hi> He could not, at that Distance, see me so often as he would; so that, when I came to <hi>Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen</hi> Years of Age, he thought, by Disposing me in Marriage, to bring me nearer him.</p>
                     <p>The Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi> had but one Son; and the intimate Friendship between my Father and him, induc'd them to think of a stricter Allyance. Our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes were equal: And the Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi>'s Son being Return'd out of <hi>Italy,</hi> his Father acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him with his Design of Marrying him. His Affection was no way Engag'd to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: And the Business was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on without my Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62767:45"/>who was look't upon as too Young to be Consulted with, in a Cause of that Nature. Yet, Madam, my Heart was sensible so Early, and capable of Discerning between Person and Person; and made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by Experience, <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> do not alwayes agree.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Equippage</hi> of the Young Gentleman was no sooner rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but he came where I was. Being not in Love, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting much Pleasure in wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on a Mistriss he had never seen, and was represented to him as a Child, he pray'd Three of his Friends to Honour his Nuptials with their Presence: The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was one of them. When they Arriv'd, my Looks were divided between several Men, all much of an Age,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62767:46"/>and equally unknown to me. I knew well enough, the Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi>'s Son was design'd my Husband; and I presently wish'd He were the Man whom I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards knew to be the <hi>Earl of Essex;</hi> at the first Sight of whom, all my Trouble for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Marry'd so Young, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently over: He was the First spoke to me, and look'd on me more earnestly, than any of the others. This made me believe, it was as I wish'd. But I was sadly Undeceiv'd, when the Young Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi> was Presented to me. I Blush'd, and Sigh'd, not knowing the Cause. The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> did also the like: His Eyes went still in Search of me; and I was not Reserv'd enough to avoyd them. The Trouble I appear'd in, was attributed to the Innocence of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62767:46"/>my Age; and I quickly learnt to take care to hide it.</p>
                     <p>Our Parents being Arriv'd, we were Marry'd, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ask'd by them, If we were willing. The Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi>'s Son appear'd pleas'd with his Fortune; and, perhaps, found me more amiable than he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. I, Madam, was so in Love with the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> all I could do, was, not to hate my Husband. Yet I had the good luck, my Kindness for my Lord of <hi>Essex</hi> was not so much as sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
                     <p>'Twas believ'd, I was then sensible of no other Pleasures, but what Children delight in; but no Age is a Stranger to Love. I quickly knew what it was to have a Kindness; and soon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd, the Liberty of my Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation had been usurp'd upon.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62767:47"/>I had little joy in being so far Mistress of my self, as to wish I could love my Husband, and endeavour it; and to have an Indifference for the <hi>Earl of Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex;</hi> for all my Efforts to that purpose were vain.</p>
                     <p>The first Resolution I took, was, to avoid the sight of a Man, who could only contribute to make me more unhappy. And when he had taken his Leave with the rest of my Lord of <hi>Rutland</hi>'s Friends, I pray'd my Father to spare my Youth for some time, and not to expose me so early to the <hi>Court,</hi> where I never had been. My Desire was granted; and when my Father return'd for <hi>London,</hi> to satisfie me, they took me to <hi>Rutland.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But the Course I took, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd not the Effect I propos'd: The <hi>Idea</hi> of the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62767:47"/>accompanied me in my Solitude. And my Father-in-Law being dead, we were forc'd to go to <hi>London,</hi> after a years stay in the Countrey.</p>
                     <p>I trembled to think, I should see the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> again; and resolv'd with my self, I would be the most retir'd Person on Earth, to avoid all Occasions of meeting him; when News was brought me, He was gone with the Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> into the <hi>Low-Countreys.</hi> The <hi>Queen</hi> receiv'd me with that Kindness She usually expresses to those She intends to Honour. I admir'd Her Merit; and the pleasure to see my self respected by Her, sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended a while my secret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes.</p>
                     <p>But within less than half a year, my Father died, and (soon after) my Husband. I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62767:48"/>was much afflicted at these Los<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses: I bewail'd my Father's Death a long time: And if I had not for my Husband that great Kindness, which is rarely met with in Marriages of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, my Reason, and his Complaisance had forc'd me to esteem him, and to express Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments sincere enough, to save me the trouble of any just Reproach from my self, or any other.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> having told me She desir'd to have me near Her, I quitted my House for an Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this Palace; and my Fortune (which was very consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable) gave me such Charms, as drew about me a number of Suitors, who pretended mighty Kindness for me; but were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally rather a Trouble, than Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to me.</p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62767:48"/>
                     <p>In this Condition was I, when the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> return'd to <hi>London.</hi> The <hi>Queens</hi> Army had been victorious; and She or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd a publick Thanksgiving, when the Generals arriv'd. I waited on Her to St. <hi>Pauls;</hi> and had not the power by any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, to be so reserv'd, as not to single out from all the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the Kingdom, the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> alone, to fix my Eyes on.</p>
                     <p>The morrow, he was one of the first to wait on the <hi>Queen:</hi> I was with Her before. I was mov'd at the sight of him: We lookt on one another several times, with equal Concern. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> (said he, as soon as he could speak to me) <hi>I have not had a moments liberty to signifie to you, how great a share I bear in your Losses. I believe</hi> (answer'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62767:49"/>I) <hi>you are sorry for my Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. 'Tis natural for every one to be concern'd for such a Person as you are</hi> (adds he:) <hi>But, Madam, I am much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd than any other.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> interrupted us: But in all the Respects the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> paid Her, I could not but observe his Eye was towards me. I confess, I was glad to see him so eager; and perhaps, I answer'd him a little too soon: But I was young, tender, and Independent. His Merits were then extraordinary; and he had the advantage of my first Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
                     <p>He came the same day to see me in my Apartment; and fail'd not to do it constantly after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. All his Actions perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me, at length, that he lov'd me; and it was not long, ere he let me know it.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62767:49"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Madam,</hi> (said he one Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, having brought me to my Chamber, after I had left the <hi>Queen</hi>) <hi>Do you remember the time we accompany'd the Earl of</hi> Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>to your Countrey-House? I have not forgot, Sir,</hi> (answer'd I) <hi>that you were one of them that did him that Honour. Is that all you remember of it?</hi> (adds he.) <hi>Did you observe nothing in my Eyes worthy taking notice of? And, Was it possible, you should inspire into me so much Love, without feeling the power of it in your self? The Friendship I had for the Earl of</hi> Rutland, <hi>and the Progress he had made, prevented my speaking of it. Yet Time and Absence have but increas'd my Passion: And I protest sincerely, from the first moment I saw you, my Heart was never affected with any but your self.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62767:50"/>
                     <p>A Discourse of this nature, may perhaps be thought unsuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Condition I was then in; who mourn'd for a <hi>Father,</hi> and a <hi>Husband:</hi> Yet I had not the power to be offended with it. The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> assur'd me, I had gain'd his Affection: I was willing to gain his, and I car'd for no more.</p>
                     <p>You will give me leave, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, to pass over my Answers; and tell you only, The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was very well satisfi'd with them; that we then settled the Correspondence we have so long maintain'd; and that we found Occasions, and Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to polish and perfect it.</p>
                     <p>Thus far you see me ignorant of the <hi>Queens</hi> Inclinations: I, as well as others, attributed the Favour we saw the <hi>Earl of Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex</hi> was in, to his Services, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62767:50"/>his Dexterity in setting them out to advantage. But in time, I perceiv'd my Mistake: And as reserv'd as the <hi>Queen</hi> was, found out the Mystery, and trembled at the Discovery.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> had an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated <hi>Soul,</hi> and capable of Greatness. Ambition might rob me of him; and I was willing to fortifie my self against all Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, and to reserve only an Esteem for him. But, What Hopes of doing that now, which all my Reason, and two years Marriage, had not effected?</p>
                     <p>At last, Jealousie succeeded my Fears; and I began to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, the Respects the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> had for the <hi>Queen,</hi> might proceed from a secret Affection. I fretted at this, and griev'd at the Heart: The <hi>Earl</hi> perceiv'd it, and solicited me long to tell
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62767:51"/>him the Cause. I refus'd as long as I was able. <hi>I am jealous,</hi> (said I to him, at last, with a little Heat) <hi>and afraid I shall lose your Affection. 'Tis not an Ʋnhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> (answers he) <hi>to see you love me so, as to doubt of me: But there is no Cause to question my Faithfulness, who never lov'd any but you. The</hi> Queen <hi>loves you,</hi> (said I;) <hi>and Her Kindness for you, with the advantage of Her Grandeur, may be dangerous Temptations to your Perseverance. The</hi> Queen <hi>love me, Madam!</hi> (replyes he) <hi>How you interpret her ordinary Bounty, which hath (perhaps) too generously recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens'd my Services beyond their Merit? She is too Haughty, and too Great a Mistress of Her Self, to fall into such a Weakness. You know, what Illustrious Allyances She hath slighted; and are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62767:51"/>She is above the reach of Love. There is not a</hi> Monarch <hi>on Earth, but I would prefer you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> (answer'd I;) <hi>and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring the</hi> Queens <hi>Affection by mine, I am easily perswaded, She may do so too. Her Eye is always upon you, spite of all Her Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and is never else satisfi'd; and I have observed some Sighs from Her, which a Heart concern'd as mine, cannot hear without Trouble. I did not till now know how happy I was,</hi> (says the Earl of <hi>Essex;) but your Jealousie makes me sensible of it. Yet, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, give me leave to assure you, You have no Cause for it. Were the</hi> Queen <hi>weak, as you imagine; did She offer me Her Crown, and Her Kindness; I would, by my Refusal, let you see (though I have Ambition) my Love for you infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely exceeds it. To satisfie you of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62767:52"/>your Mistake, allow me to procure Her Consent to our Marriage. You have mourn'd long enough, to avoid all Imputations of Indecency: It is in your power, to make me the happiest of Men, and to clear all the Doubts you have of my Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was far from opposing the Proposal he made; and if I was not fully convinc'd the <hi>Queen</hi> was not in Love with him, yet I thought, if She was, he knew it not.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To let you see,</hi> (adds he) <hi>I will not conceal from you any Kindness the</hi> Queen <hi>hath exprest for me; I declare, I sacrifice to you one of the handsomest Ladies of the</hi> Court, <hi>who hath a thousand ways invited my Love.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I prest him to let me know her Name; but he conjur'd me to be satisfi'd with what he had
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62767:52"/>said; and, not to force him to further Indiscretion, I gave over Pressing him.</p>
                     <p>[<hi rend="margQuotes">The Countess of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Blush't at this Part of the Discourse, having Reason to believe her self the Person intended. She Hated him the more for't; but had the Command of her self, not to interrupt the Countess of <hi>Essex;</hi> who proceeded in her Story.</hi>]</p>
                     <p>This Freedom of the <hi>Earl</hi> put an End to my Suspicions. I left him to take his Time, for speaking to the <hi>Queen:</hi> When he went to Thank Her for the Government of <hi>Ireland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow'd on him, he return'd to me with a Transport of Joy, to tell me; <hi>The</hi> Queen <hi>had not only Consented to his Desires, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62767:53"/>to make the Earl of</hi> Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester <hi>King of</hi> England, This quieted my Spirit, and made me acknowledge, I had no Cause to be Jealous.</p>
                     <p>We spent some dayes with a great deal of Pleasure; but were Cruelly interrupted by the Order the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to go into <hi>France,</hi> to Command the Forces the <hi>Queen</hi> sent in Aid of that <hi>King.</hi> I had not time to Express my grief to him, or to be a Witness of his. We parted in Haste: And then it was, I repented I had Believ'd him; and that the <hi>Queens</hi> Coldness towards me, convinc'd me of the Truth of my former Suspicions: and that Her sending away the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> was but to Remove him from me.</p>
                     <p>I left <hi>Court,</hi> as soon as I could,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62767:53"/>with Decency, ask the <hi>Queen</hi> Leave to retire into a House of my Fathers, about Fifty Miles from <hi>London.</hi> I will not tell you, how I was Alarm'd at the News of the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> his Death, in his Return from <hi>Spain;</hi> nor how we Writ to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in his Absence. I was ready to Dye for Grief, when he Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at my House more Respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and more Amorous then he had ever appear'd.</p>
                     <p>He would have put me out of my Opinion, concerning the <hi>Queen:</hi> But I obstinately main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd it True. When I had Convinc'd him of it, he offer'd to leave <hi>England</hi> if I would name a Place where we might Live quietly. I had Affection enough, to incline me to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to this Proposal: But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering it Unjust in me to spoil
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62767:54"/>the Progress of his Good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and put an End to his Hopes by an Unexcusable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, I told him, it was impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible. And ushering with a Sigh the Advice I was going to him: <hi>Forget me, Sir,</hi> (said I) <hi>for I see, your Fate will force you to it. The</hi> Queen <hi>will still Cross us, and never want Pretence to Separate us: 'Tis better breaking off an Engagement, that suits not with your Affairs. Nothing in the World, can be a greater Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to me; but I will submit to it, if it be for your Good. You suspect me of Indifference,</hi> (said he, interrupting me;) <hi>and you have the Cruelty to Advise me to it. Did you love me more, you would Know me better: And were I capable of doing an unjust Thing, I believe you would Exhort me to forget you, for no other Cause,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62767:54"/>but that you might think of me no more. But,</hi> Madam, <hi>to shorten cur Discourse, and our Doubts, which almost make me Mad; Believe it, I Love you above all things in the World: There is a Sure and Easie Way to satisfie you of it. You are not willing to go with me out of</hi> England; <hi>and yet you are still afraid of the</hi> Queen: <hi>Let us Marry Privately, and Conceal it till we see a more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Time. This will Trustrate the</hi> Queens <hi>Designs to our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice; You will no longer doubt of my Affection: And if the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness be Discover'd, 'tis but flying out of the Reach of the Resent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments we fear.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was strangely mov'd at this Discourse: Every thing oblig'd me to believe him. Yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering it would reflect upon my Reputation to be privately
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62767:55"/>Marryed, I was afraid to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. The <hi>Earl</hi> Complain'd of me; I Cry'd: <hi>Love</hi> was our Arbitratour, and Decided the Controversie in his Favour. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long Resistance, I agreed to a Private Marriage; on Condition the <hi>Earl</hi> would go for <hi>London</hi> on the Morrow; and appear dis-engag'd to the <hi>Queen</hi> from all the Kindness he had had for me. We agreed to be Marry'd at the Earl of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampton</hi>'s, his particular Friend; where I was to stay, while he went for <hi>London.</hi> Thus we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. He took <hi>London</hi>-Road; I went for <hi>Southampton,</hi> Attended by <hi>Tracy,</hi> a Domestick of the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>'s, in whom he repos'd an entire Confidence.</p>
                     <p>As the <hi>Earl</hi> was on the Road, he had Leisure to consider what Measures to take. My Lord
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62767:55"/>
                        <hi>Southampton</hi> came to to Receive me at his House; where the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> Arriv'd, soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had obtain'd Leave from the <hi>Queen,</hi> to Absent himself a few Dayes.</p>
                     <p>We are now come to the Instant, that usher'd in our Cros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. We were Marrry'd in the Presence of my Lord <hi>Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Tracy,</hi> and some Women of mine, and a Kinsman of the <hi>Earl of Essex.</hi> He gave me an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, how the <hi>Queen</hi> had Receiv'd him; and began to confess, he believ'd, She Lov'd him.</p>
                     <p>He staied but six Dayes at <hi>Southampton;</hi> in which Time we agreed what Course to take.</p>
                     <p>I was too far from <hi>London,</hi> to see the <hi>Earl</hi> often, without Discovering our Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62767:56"/>Nothing seem'd more proper to Conceal it, than a House he had within few Miles of <hi>London,</hi> on the <hi>Thames</hi> Side: It stood alone, and was Strong enough to prevent a Surprize. Having settled my Affairs, I was Conducted thither by my Lord <hi>Southampton,</hi> and <hi>Tracy,</hi> while the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> return'd for <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nothing could be more Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, than the Solitude I was in. My Lord of <hi>Essex</hi> came to see me every Day: And I spent there Two Years, without a Moments Trouble. At last, an Accident happen'd that Misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly perplext us.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> had an Infinite of Enemies, who En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd him; and for all his Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they took Notice of his Extraordinary Assiduity for the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62767:56"/>place I was in. They told the <hi>Queen</hi> of it. She was disturb'd at it; more, perhaps, for the Suspicion She had of some Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Gallantry of his there, than for those Matters they would have Possest Her with.</p>
                     <p>I gave Her no Trouble: The <hi>Earl</hi>'s Dis-engagement, with my Pretended Journey into <hi>France,</hi> had secur'd Her as to me. Yet She would go see whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Earl</hi> frequented that House, only for the Pleasure of the Place, or some hidden Cause.</p>
                     <p>One Day, as the <hi>Earl</hi> was with Her, She gave Orders, Her ordinary Retinue should be ready to Wait on Her. <hi>I have long had a mind to see your Country-House,</hi> (sayes She to the Earl;) <hi>I have had a very Pleasant Description of it: The
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62767:57"/>Weather is Fair; and, I believe, a Walk so far, may do Me good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You may Imagine the Fears this put the <hi>Earl</hi> in: He durst not openly Oppose Her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign; but endeavoured to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Her, by saying, <hi>His House deserv'd not the Pains it would cost Her, to go so far.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When he saw Her resolv'd upon it, he begg'd Leave to go before, to put things in order for Her Reception. <hi>No,</hi> (sayes She) <hi>you shall be My Guide: There's no need of Preparation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl,</hi> at these Words, trembled for me. He was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of all Means of Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And the Concern he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd in, made the <hi>Queen</hi> more Curious.</p>
                     <p>Imagine what a Trouble he was in by the way, and how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten he wisht something might
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62767:57"/>hinder their Arrival. But For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune favour'd the <hi>Queens</hi> Designs so far, that they came safe to the House; and She would present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go see the Lodgings. The Earl astonisht, gave Her his Hand. The Chamber I us'd, was the best in the House; and the first the <hi>Queen</hi> stay'd at. The Earl seeing no Remedy, steps to the Door, (which he found open, contrary to Custom) and was pleasingly surpriz'd, to find only <hi>Tracy</hi> there, sleeping, or rather pretending to sleep, on a Couch. He was quickly awak'd; and having exprest his Surprize, and Respect, immediately withdrew.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> who thought him at <hi>London,</hi> began to take Heart, fancying his good <hi>Genius</hi> had reveal'd the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to <hi>Tracy.</hi> But a new Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble arose: My Picture hung in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62767:58"/>the same Room, under a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. The <hi>Queen</hi> askt, <hi>If it was the</hi> Earl's? He answer'd, with some Trouble, <hi>It was not.</hi> The <hi>Queen</hi> drew the Curtain, and saw Her Self drawn at length, where the Earl thought my Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture would appear. Then it was, he was perswaded, the faithful <hi>Tracy</hi> had had an Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Journey.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> exprest much Joy, to see Her Picture in the <hi>Earl</hi>'s Chamber.</p>
                     <p>From the House, She went into the Garden; took a short Repast, (during which, <hi>Tracy</hi> found the opportunity to whis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the Earl, <hi>He need not trouble himself</hi>—) and return'd to <hi>London,</hi> without the least suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</p>
                     <p>Thus Matters pass'd on their Side. As to ours, The very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62767:58"/>the <hi>Queen</hi> told the <hi>Earl of Essex, She would see his House,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Southampton</hi> was at Her Chamber-door. <hi>You are come in very good time, to go along with the</hi> Queen <hi>to the Earl of</hi> Essex<hi>'s,</hi> says the Officer, who was going to provide the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page.</p>
                     <p>The Earl of <hi>Southampton,</hi> by these few words, quickly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd the Storm that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Friend: And to provide a Remedy; <hi>I am not very well,</hi> (said he to the Officer:) <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the</hi> Queen <hi>may command me to wait on Her; I will not go into Her Presence. Pray, Let Her not know, you have seen me.</hi> The Officer promis'd, <hi>She should not;</hi> and <hi>Southampton</hi> hastned to the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>'s, to tell <hi>Tracy;</hi> who immediately took the best Horse his Master had;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62767:59"/>and put him so well to it, that he was with me before the <hi>Queen</hi> left <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was not a little troubled at the News. <hi>Tracy</hi> hid me, and my Women in a Quarter, where was no likelihood of our being discover'd; and then chang'd the <hi>Queens</hi> Picture for mine.</p>
                     <p>That Evening, the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> came to see me, and gave me an Account of the Tortures he had that day endur'd for me; and how <hi>Southampton</hi> and <hi>Tracy</hi> had deliver'd him out of them.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Irish</hi> rebell'd; I lay in at that time: The <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> (who lov'd me no less than his Glory) had within himself de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate Conflicts. His Duty pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd: He desir'd he might Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Army, the <hi>Queen</hi> granted it; and the same time, plainly declar'd her Affection
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62767:59"/>for him; which I was before but too well assur'd of. She gave him abundance of very kind Expressions; and (to confirm the truth of them) a <hi>Ring,</hi> which still leaves the poor <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> some Hopes.</p>
                     <p>He was sufficiently prepar'd to manage the <hi>Queen:</hi> And you see, by this time, Madam, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was not under a necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of some Dissimulation.</p>
                     <p>He gave me a faithful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, of all pass'd between them; and being fearful for me in his absence, he resolv'd to remove me, and to go himself out of <hi>England,</hi> if Matters were discover'd.</p>
                     <p>This put him on Search of some Places of Refuge. The King of <hi>Scots</hi> promis'd him, among others, the Palace of <hi>Dimbourg.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Tyrone</hi>
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62767:60"/>made him many Proposals: But certain it is, he never hearkned to any of them.</p>
                     <p>I was weak when he left me; and oblig'd to recover a little Strength, before I would under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a Voyage for <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I was on my way, Fortune stay'd me, the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was Charg'd with several Matters; and the <hi>Queen,</hi> prepossest by our Enemies, took our innocent Precautions for Crimes.</p>
                     <p>At last, Madam, the <hi>Earl</hi> was forc'd to come, and shut him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self up in the Place where I was; and was resolv'd to perish, in defence of me.</p>
                     <p>You know what follow'd. Consider the Frights I was in, amidst so much Trouble and Bloud, I saw every day spilt.</p>
                     <p>The Earl conjur'd me inces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly, to quit a Place, where
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62767:60"/>he could not make any long De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence against so great Forces, as were imploy'd to take it.</p>
                     <p>I exhorted him to yield, and implore the <hi>Queens</hi> Goodness. He protested, <hi>He would never do it, till I was in a Place of Safety.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus was I forc'd to leave him, and go for <hi>Dimbourg.</hi> The faithful <hi>Tracy,</hi> who should have conducted me thither, had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risht already, in maintaining the Interests of his Master.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> committed me to the Charge of one of his Kinsmen: They forc'd me out of his Arms, to put me aboard a Boat, that waited for us on the <hi>Thames,</hi> and was to carry us to the Place where our Convoy attended us.</p>
                     <p>My Fears, and my Grief put me into a Fever: This staid me some Dayes, at a little Village;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62767:61"/>where I had News of the <hi>Earl</hi>'s Imprisonment, and the <hi>Queens</hi> Resolution to Ruine him.</p>
                     <p>The Extremity of my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spair, put me on the Resolution of Presenting my self to the <hi>Queen,</hi> and endeavouring to obtain some Favour by an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Confession. But, Madam, you know, I found in Her, no Disposition to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don us.</p>
                     <p>My Conduct hath produc'd a terrible Effect: And I may justly Reproach my self, to have been the Cause of all my Lord of <hi>Essex</hi> his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="narration">
                     <p>This Discourse ended in Tears. The Countess of <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi> took small Care to stop them: She was too much Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62767:61"/>in more than one Part of the Story, which heightened her Fury: And leaving the Countess of <hi>Essex</hi> to the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Despair, she return'd to the <hi>Queen,</hi> whom she found almost drown'd in Hers. She us'd all her Art, to Revive the <hi>Queens</hi> Anger; and by her Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Address, effected her Design, without saying a Word directly against the Criminal.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cecil</hi> and <hi>She</hi> were Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to see the Execution de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>What shall we do Madam,</hi> (sayes he to her) <hi>if the</hi> Queen, <hi>in the Height of Her Anger, will not give way that Justice be done? What are we to expect, when Her Anger is over? What are we not to fear from Her Love, if it once get the Mastery of a Heart, as Hers is? 'Tis no where so Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62767:62"/>no where so Absolute; and I very much doubt, whether all our Caution can prevent the ill Effects of it. In a word, Condemn'd as the</hi> Earl of Essex <hi>is, by an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust Assembly, 'tis possible, he may Recover his former Favour with the</hi> Queen, <hi>and utterly Ruin us, as soon as he sets Footing at</hi> Court. <hi>I shall bestir my self a little, ere that come to pass,</hi> (sayes the Countess of <hi>Nottingham;</hi>) <hi>I have the</hi> Queens <hi>Ear: I know how to speak; I am not suspected; nor am I a Stranger to the Secrets of the One, nor the Other: Yet we are not to Flatter our selves; the</hi> Earl of Essex <hi>is Master of his Fortune: If he Petition, the</hi> Queen <hi>will not have the Power to deny him. He hath a</hi> Pledge, <hi>which gives him an Absolute Power over Her: But, thanks to his Pride, he will not make use
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62767:62"/>of it. Besides Whom can he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy in an Affair of this Nature, but we can Corrupt? I will not leave the</hi> Queen; <hi>and, I'le Pawn my Life, I will Secure all with Her. Do your part, and let's not be Surpriz'd.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cecil</hi> knew the Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> too well, to doubt of what she said: He parted better satisfi'd; and thought of nothing, but what flatter'd their Common Hatred against <hi>Essex.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> had had a very ill Night, tormented equally with Sickness and Trouble. She consider'd the Unfaithfulness of the <hi>Earl of Essex;</hi> his Plotting against Her Authority, his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Marriage, his Giving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self wholly up to the Pleasures of it, (while he pretended to be Entirely at Her Devotion)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62767:63"/>and his Pride in the Depth of Misfortunes.</p>
                     <p>She thought sometimes these Reflections strong enough, to Enable Her to see him Dye. But presently, the Pleasing <hi>Idea</hi> of him She would destroy, his Merit, his Services, and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Inclination She had for him, Inspir'd Her again with gentle Resolutions. She thought it better see him a Criminal, then never see him more. The thoughts of his Execution put Her almost besides Her Self, though it was in Her Power to prevent it.</p>
                     <p>The Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> was as Wakeful as the <hi>Queen,</hi> though for very different Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; and waiting on Her in the Morning, as usual, <hi>You find Me in a Lamentable Condition</hi> (sayes the <hi>Queen;</hi>) <hi>and if you
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62767:63"/>help not to Comfort Me, I shall not be able to endure it much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The Wretch, who causes Me all this Trouble, is alwayes before My Eyes, in the most pitiful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition imaginable. It is possible, I should do nothing for him in such an Extremity? Shall I permit him to Perish, as if I had no more Valued him than another; when I have Declar'd to him, I Lov'd him? Shall I Reproach My self one Day, with Cruelty to have Forsaken him, when it was in My Power to Save him? What Your Majesty shall be Pleas'd to do in his Favour</hi> (replyes the Countess of <hi>Nottingham,</hi>) <hi>will be the more Generous, for that he hath not Solicited it. If he Petition'd, Your Bounty would be look't upon as an Effect of Your Pity, and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions: But now, it will proceed purely from Your Goodness,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62767:64"/>
                     <p>These words effected partly what she aim'd at. The <hi>Queen</hi> blush'd, sigh'd, and was silent a while.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It must be confest</hi> (proceeds She,) <hi>That to do all for him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out putting him to the cost of one Sign of Repentance, is to approve of his Pride, and encourage him to carry it on to the highest Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. He would have My Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness do all; and without any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion on the Outrages he hath done Me, he believes, I shall think My Self too happy, in holding the Executioner's Hand. Never doubt, Madam,</hi> (says the Countess) <hi>but he makes account to triumph still over that Goodness Your Majesty hath always made appear towards him. Had he been carried from</hi> Westminster <hi>to the Scaffold; had You given him a sight of that Scene of Death, and pardon'd</hi> Southamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62767:64"/>
                        <hi>without respiting the other's Execution, he would have been glad to make use of any means, in his power, to move You to mercy. But he knows the power he hath over You; and pretends, that by receiving a Pardon he vouchsafes not to Petition for, all the World will believe him innocent. But, Madam, if Matters be carried on thus, What will be thought of the Justice of the Kingdom? What will the World judge of Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty? There is not a Person ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of this Adventure: And, if the</hi> Earl of Essex, <hi>without ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his Crimes, sees him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self at liberty; Will it not be said, That</hi> England <hi>is govern'd by a</hi> Queen, <hi>not so discreet, as Fame reports Her to be?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>At this, <hi>Cecil</hi> arriv'd, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifi'd extreamly the Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi>'s Party: He secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62767:65"/>her with all the Art of a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Eloquence, to perswade the <hi>Queen, She was concern'd in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the</hi> Earl of Essex <hi>should die.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Queen,</hi> in a Pet, consent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he should be Executed sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly; and <hi>Cecil</hi> lost no time, in carrying Her Orders to those who were to be Actors in the Execution.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> (as the Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> had shrewdly guess'd) had no Thoughts of Petitioning for a Favour, which, in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Queens</hi> Kindness would of it self freely grant him. But when he saw himself on the point of being carry'd to the Place of Execution, he thought it his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not to neglect the Medicines he had in his power, to bring about the <hi>Queen.</hi> Then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd to implore Her Mercy,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62767:65"/>and put Her in mind of Her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises and Oaths. And knowing the Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> was Her Favourite and Confident; though he had Cause to believe, she had no great Kindness for him, he was perswaded, she might have Generosity enough, to serve him in this important Mediation.</p>
                     <p>He sent to desire the Favour of a Visit from her. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tess, impatient to know the Cause, went directly to him, without acquainting the <hi>Queen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Who but a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> could have seen the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi>'s Person, and at the same time known his Misfortune, without being melted into Compassion? Yet the Countess of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> at the sight of him, was all Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Revenge: But, feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing some Sweetness, she gave
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62767:66"/>him way to declare himself thus:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Can you, Madam, pardon the most unfortunate of Men the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he gives you at a time, when he hath no Cause to flatter himself you have any Remains of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for him? Yet nothing can be now of greater Advantage to me, than your Protection. I know the Power you have over the</hi> Queen; <hi>and would you be pleas'd to joyn it to my Sorrow, and Repentance, for having offended Her, I doubt not, but we may prevail much. Tell Her then, Madam,</hi> (conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues he, putting his Knee to the Ground) <hi>That you have seen me in this suppliant Posture, full of Grief for having deserv'd Her Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. Restore Her this <hi>Ring,</hi> which I have kept; and entreat Her to remember the Promises She made, when She gave it me. I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62767:66"/>beg my Life by this <hi>Pledge,</hi> and She cannot deny it me, without forgetting Her Oaths. I can no longer look on Life, as a thing pleasing to me; but a miserable Wife, and the Interest of a Son, press me to continue it, as long as I can. I cannot think, the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the One, or Infancy of the Other, needs my Justification: The Favour to be begg'd of the</hi> Queen, <hi>is for me alone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> was transported with Joy, to see the <hi>Earl</hi> trust her with the <hi>Ring,</hi> which had so often Alarm'd her, and whose Power <hi>Cecil</hi> was still afraid of. She frankly promis'd what she had not the least intent to do for <hi>Essex,</hi> added feign'd Tears to her false Promises; and assur'd him, she would directly go use her utmost Interest with the <hi>Queen,</hi> in his Favour.</p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:62767:67"/>
                     <p>But instead of going to the <hi>Queen,</hi> to give Her an Account of her Visit, she went to <hi>Cecil;</hi> who waited for her, prais'd her Cruelty, and had the pleasure to see in his power, the sole Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacle against <hi>Essex</hi>'s Death.</p>
                     <p>They went together to the <hi>Queen,</hi> who asking, <hi>How</hi> Essex <hi>receiv'd Her last Orders?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He was never observ'd so haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Madam,</hi> (answers <hi>Cecil;) he cannot prevail with himself, to shew the least Sign of Repentance. He thinks of nothing but his Wife, and she is the whole Subject of his Discourse to those who go to him. Let him die then, let him perish,</hi> (says the <hi>Queen,</hi> very angry) <hi>since he will have it so. Let Me be eas'd of the tormenting Ʋncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties and Disquiets I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I am no longer against his Execution.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:62767:67"/>
                     <p>This zealous Minister was unwilling to leave the <hi>Queen</hi> the least time of Reflexion: And while the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was in Expectation of the Effect of the promises of the Unfaithful Countess of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision was made for his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>Tower,</hi> to avoid a Rebellion among the People, who lov'd him.</p>
                     <p>His Soul was naturally great, and discover'd not the least Weakness, in the last Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                     <p>Never did Man go to his Death with more Constancy and Firmness. He did not Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, in the least, against the <hi>Queen;</hi> though he might have Reproach't Her with Promises. He mounted the <hi>Scaffold</hi> Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, Undrest himself, Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his Family to those a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62767:68"/>him; and having drawn Tears from all Eyes that were Spectatours of that last Act of his Life, he receiv'd his Death, without so much as giving way his Eyes should be Cover'd.</p>
                     <p>Thus Dy'd this Famous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> One of the best Qualifi'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons in the World; and a Man who had been too Happy, had not <hi>Love</hi> had too great a power over him.</p>
                     <p>Soon after the <hi>Queen</hi> had Consented he should be Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, She Relaps'd into Her former Irresolutions; and after a sharp Conflict within Her Self, She resolv'd to Pardon him; and sent an Officer of Her Guards, to forbid their Proceeding fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But it was too late: <hi>Cecil</hi> had fore-seen what might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and Cruelly provided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62767:68"/>the Effects of Her Relapse into former Kindness. The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> was already Executed; and that was the Answer he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd to the <hi>Queen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then it was, She lost Her ordinary Moderation; then Her Grief broke out Publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cecil,</hi> (sayes She) <hi>What Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief hath your Barbarous Zeal, and Impatience, done Me?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>With that, She burst out into Tears, and would not endure the Caresses, or the Comforts of any about Her.</p>
                     <p>While the <hi>Queen</hi> abhorr'd Her Self, for the Orders Her Anger had given, <hi>Cecil,</hi> who had so faithfully caus'd them to be Executed, enjoy'd the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of having Procur'd them: And the Countess of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Triumph'd in her self, for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62767:69"/>the Revenge she had taken of a Man, who had slighted her Charms.</p>
                     <p>'Tis impossible to Express the Grief of the Countess of <hi>Essex:</hi> The most Stony Hearts had Tears for her. The <hi>Queen,</hi> (whose Anger was dead with the <hi>Earl</hi>) sent to Comfort her, and assure her, she was at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and might Dispose of her Husband's Estate.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let Her take my Life, and keep Her Pity to Her Self,</hi> (sayes the <hi>Countess</hi> to the <hi>Queens</hi> Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger:) <hi>She hath Rob'd me of all that made my Life dear to me; and 'tis not in Her Power, to Repair the Mischief She hath done me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> his Friends, finding her, at present, inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Comfort, (even from them whom she Esteem'd high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62767:69"/>for their Love to the <hi>Earl</hi>) took her from <hi>London;</hi> in hopes, that Time might make her Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible of that Consolation, which the Violence of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Sorrows render'd altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vain.</p>
                     <p>As for the <hi>Queen,</hi> She lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish'd out the rest of Her Life: The only Comfort She had, was to think the <hi>Earl of Essex,</hi> had slighted Her to his Death, and never made Her any Submission.</p>
                     <p>The Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> had small Joy of her Faithless Life. A violent Malady seiz'd her, and made her sensible of the Horrours of Death: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morse of Conscience tormented her; the Ghost of the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> (whose Death her Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty occasion'd) seem'd to Haunt her incessantly. And being at the point of Death, she could
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62767:70"/>not Depart, without Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging her Crime to the <hi>Queen.</hi> Having beg'd one Moment's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, she confest all that pass'd between the <hi>Earl of Essex</hi> and <hi>Her,</hi> the Love she had for him, the Implacable Hatred that suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded it, and her Perfidious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in keeping the <hi>Ring</hi> he had Trusted her with. With that, she presented the <hi>Ring</hi> to the <hi>Queen;</hi> who was ready to dye at the Receiving it; and was within very little of making the dying Countess feel the violence of Her Resentment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wretch,</hi> (crves She, with Looks full of Indignation) <hi>What Remorse hast thou expos'd Me to! Where Heaven will Pardon thy Crimes, I know not; sure I am, I shall never forget them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Having thus said, the <hi>Queen</hi> went out, and the Countess in few Hours Dyed.</p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:62767:70"/>
                     <p>This prov'd a Mortal Blow to the <hi>Queens</hi> Health; who not long after Dyed, uncomforted for the Death of the <hi>Earl of Essex.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cecil</hi> had lov'd the Countess of <hi>Nottingham</hi> too well, to be easily Comforted for hers.</p>
                     <p>By the Death of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> the Crown of <hi>England</hi> pass'd into the Illustrious House of the <hi>Stuatts,</hi> whose Right it was. King <hi>James,</hi> after a Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reign, left it to His Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity, for the Repose of His Kingdoms.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:71"/>
                  <list>
                     <head>Books Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>M. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Russel-Street,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <item>AN Earnest Request to Mr. <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith,</hi> occasioned by a Sermon of his Preached before His Majesty.</item>
                     <item>Falshood Unmasqued; or, an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to Truth Unvailed.</item>
                     <item>The Reverend Dr. <hi>Patrick's</hi> Fast-Sermon, <hi>Nov.</hi> 13.</item>
                     <item>The History of the Passion, in <hi>Octa.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plato's</hi> Apology for <hi>Socrates,</hi> in <hi>Octa.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dr. Whitby</hi> of Idolatry, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dr. Whitby's</hi> Answer to Mr. <hi>Cressey</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Chamberlain's</hi> Poems, in <hi>Octa.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Moral Essayes, in 3 Volums, in 12.</item>
                     <item>A Prospect of Humane Misery, in 12</item>
                     <item>Vanity of Honour, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Bishop <hi>Andrew</hi>'s Devotions, in 12.</item>
                     <item>The Princess of <hi>Cleve,</hi> the most Famed <hi>Romance,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Memoires of Madam <hi>Maria Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chini,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Heroine Musqueteer, in 4 Parts, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Happy Slave, in 3 Parts in 12.</item>
                     <item>The Disorders of Love, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:62767:71"/>
                     <item>The Triumphs of Love, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Zelinda,</hi> A Romance, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Brion;</hi> or, The Cheating Gallant, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Obliging Mistress, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fatal Prudence, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Count <hi>Gabalis,</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Double Cuckold, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Pilgrim, A Novel, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Earl of <hi>Essex,</hi> and Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth;</hi> A Novel, in two Parts.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plays Written by</hi> John Dryden, <hi>Esq;</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Limberham,</hi> or, The <hi>Kind-Keeper.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oedipus,</hi> in part.</item>
                     <item>Mistaken Husband, in part.</item>
                     <item>Notes on <hi>Morocco.</hi> in part.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plays Written by Mr.</hi> Lee.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nero,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Glorian,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Rival-Queens,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mythridates,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Caesar Borgia,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sophonisba;</hi> or, <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oedipus,</hi> in part.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Theodosius;</hi> or, The Force of <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Andromache,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:62767:72"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Calisto,</hi> A Masque at Court.</item>
                     <item>Countrey-Wit▪ A Comedy.</item>
                     <item>Destruction of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> in 2 Parts.</item>
                     <item>The Miseries of Civil-War.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plays Written by Mrs.</hi> Bhen.
<list>
                           <item>Forced Marriage, A Tragi-Comedy</item>
                           <item>Town-Fop, A Comedy.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Abdellazar,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
                           <item>Madam <hi>Fickle,</hi> Comedies.</item>
                           <item>Fond Husband, Comedies.</item>
                           <item>Vertuous Wife, Comedies.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Plain-Dealer, A Comedy, By Mr. <hi>Wicherly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fool turn'd Critick.</item>
                     <item>Esq; <hi>Old Sap;</hi> or, The Night-Adventures.</item>
                     <item>All Mistaken, By M. <hi>Howard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>English</hi> Monsieur, By M. <hi>Howard.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Generous Enemies, A Comedy; By Mr. <hi>Corey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tartuff,</hi> A Comedy; By Mr. <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn. In the Press.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Rival-Mother, A Novel.</item>
                     <item>A Perfect School for the Officers of the Mouth.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, with the Murder of the Duke of <hi>Gloucester.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A Tragedy in Heroick-Verse: Written by two Ladies.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:62767:72"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>